Sir!
爷
News from the borders.
边疆传来消息了
Our informant says
咱们的眼说
that Qiu Yi developed heat illness
秋宜在被流放的路上
on his way to Gannan.
得了热病
It has been four to five days.
已经有四五日了
A physician tended to him, but he still hasn't gotten any better.
郎中瞧了还不见好
Don't tell Qiu Yan about this first.
此事先别告诉秋嫣
She won't be able to help anyway.
告诉她也帮不上忙
It'll only make her feel more troubled.
只会给她增加烦恼
You're right.
对
Oh, right.
对了
How is the search for the auspicious item coming along?
之前让你找的祥瑞怎么样了
The treasure recorded in the Hongzhen Sutra
弘真经里记载的那个宝物
refers to a pearl of immortality.
是个仙珠
Our men found a large Eastpearl
之前弟兄们在大东瀛
in Japan last time.
找到一颗大东珠
But the Eastpearl was too fragile.
但是那个东珠不堪雕刻
It shattered and crumbled when the craftsmen tried to work on it.
工匠们一下刻刀就碎成粉末了
After that, we tried lapis lazuli and Amazonites,
后来又找了青金石 天河石
but they were both too common
都太过寻常
and ordinary.
不足为奇
Sir.
爷
Do you remember
你记不记得
the family heirloom back at Duke Lu's residence
之前在查抄卢国公府时的那个
when we seized the place?
传家宝
That Night-luminescent Pearl
那个夜明珠就很像
is very similar to the pearl mentioned in the Hongzhen Sutra.
弘真经里记载的仙珠
They regarded that pearl as their lifeblood.
他们家把那珠子当命根子
Sir, you were magnanimous
爷就有君子气度
and spared the pearl when you confiscated their residence.
抄家的时候就没毁了那珠子
I'm sure it must still be with Gao Yang.
想必现在还在高阳手上
I'll get our men to keep searching.
我再叫弟兄们找
The world is vast.
天下这么大
We must be able to find a pearl somehow.
还能找不出来一颗珠子吗
We're out of time.
没有时间了
Qiu Yi is a scholar. He has a weak physique.
秋宜是文人身子骨
He has had a tiring journey,
一路劳累颠簸
and he even developed heat illness in a remote place.
又在贫寒之地患上了热病
I doubt he can hold on for long.
不见得还能撑多久
Liang Yi?
梁翊
Why are you here?
你来做什么
To see how an old friend has been.
来看看故人过得好不好
I, Gao Yang,
我高阳生平
have never done anything harmful.
从来不做伤天害理之事
I'm sure I have my blessings.
自有福报
You barely make ends meet,
家中都揭不开锅了
yet you're still holding on to your family heirloom.
还守着传家宝不撒手
I wonder if I should call you tough
我真不知你是硬气呢
or a fool.
还是愚蠢
You want that pearl?
那珠子 你想要
Give me an offer.
开价吧
How much are the honor and dignity
我高氏一门的荣辱
of the Gao Family worth then?
又价值几何呢
Give it up.
你就死了这条心吧
I have nothing else to lose.
我现在没有什么可以失去的了
At worst, I'll just lose my life.
大不了一死
I never harm the innocents in the family when I carry out my duty.
我办差从来不祸及家人
When Duke Lu killed my father,
当初卢国公害死我父亲的时候
I took him down,
我扳倒他
but I spared you.
却也放了你一条生路
Why must you force yourself to your end?
你何苦把自己往死路上逼呢
I came
今日我来
to offer you a chance today.
就是来给你一次机会
If you miss it,
你若错过了
you'll never get another chance to start over again.
就再也没有翻身的机会了
Are you going to write a letter
那你要上书一封
to vindicate my father then?
为我父亲平反
Impossible.
不可能
You know His Majesty's nature.
你也应该清楚当今圣上的秉性
It is not within my power to do so
当朝之中
in the current dynasty.
这也不是我力所能及的事情
Give me a price.
说个数吧
If it was the money I was after,
我若图钱的话
I would've sold that pearl years ago.
这几年早把那珠子卖掉了
Submit a memorial, then.
那你上一道折子吧
Tell His Majesty that the Gao Family helped you
说我高家有功于你也好
or the Gao Family turned over a new leaf or something.
改过自新也罢
Ask His Majesty
请求圣上
to restore my family's name and status.
恢复我高家名誉优待
Gao Yang.
高阳
It seems you are determined to make things hard for me.
你这是铁了心让我为难啊
Yes.
对
After all, who knew that there would come a day
谁让你梁大人
when you would have to ask me of something?
终究有一天会求到我高阳呢
It is karmic retribution indeed.
真是天道好轮回啊
You ruined my family back then.
当年你害得我家破人亡
Now, I want you
如今我就是让你
to help your father's murderer with your very own hands.
亲手托起你的杀父仇人
I want to see you suffer with my own eyes.
我要亲眼看着你痛不欲生
Otherwise,
否则那珠子
you won't get even a shard of that pearl!
你连点碎渣你都得不到
Father.
父亲
Will you blame me?
您会怪我吗
When you died by Duke Lu's arrow,
当年您死于卢国公箭下时
I vowed
我向您发誓
I would have Duke Lu pay for it with his life
要让卢国公以命偿命
and ruin his name.
名誉尽毁
That I would crush the Gao Family and have them never be restored.
要让高家永世不得翻身
I am at my wits' end.
我实在没有别的办法
She is very important to me.
她对我很重要
This matter is very important to me as well.
这件事对我也很重要
Just like when I avenged you back then.
就像当年为您报仇一样
Blame me if you must.
您要怪就怪我吧
I am unfilial.
是儿子不孝
My lord!
大人
Why did you drink so much?
你怎么喝这么多酒啊
I'll have someone carry you inside.
我让人把你抬进去
No need.
不用 不用
Don't alert anyone.
别惊动任何人
Just help me inside.
你扶我进去便可
Slowly.
慢点
Are you all right?
没事吧
Why did you drink so much?
怎么喝这么多呀
I would like some water.
我想喝点水
Water...
水
All right.
好
Wait here.
你等一下啊
Here.
来
Drink some.
喝点
Where did you get this?
这是哪来的
Today,
今日
I was looking for something in the chest you kept
我在你装小时候东西的箱子里面
your childhood belongings.
找东西
I didn't know you wrote a book about investigations.
没想到你还会写公案话本啊
Do you remember when I told you
你还记得在禁苑的时候
back at the imperial park...
我同你说
What are you doing?
你干什么
I'm hungry.
我饿了
Get me something to eat.
给我弄点吃的
All right.
好
(I couldn't read much as a child,)
我小时候不大识字
(but I wanted to study.)
可我又想读书
My mother tried to cultivate my interest
我母亲为了培养我的兴趣
by having me read books about investigations.
就让我读公案话本
I remember the first one I read was a half-scroll handwritten copy.
我记得最早我看的是半卷手抄
It was called...
那名字叫
"Collection of Odd Occurrences."
叫大朔奇案录
Miss Qiu Min?
秋珉姑娘
Sir!
爷
There's a letter here!
这儿有封信
(Don't worry, Qin Xuan.)
表哥放心
(I won't take my life and cause trouble for you.)
我不会去寻短见让你为难
(I just want to find a place and hide.)
我只是想找个地方躲起来
(Perhaps hide away forever.)
也许一辈子都躲起来
(I know in your heart,)
我知道在表哥心里
(I mean only disgrace and shame.)
我只是表哥的耻辱
(But to me,)
但对我而言
(it wasn't.)
不是
(That night)
那一夜是我人生中
(was the best night of my life.)
最美好畅快的一晚
(Qin Xuan,)
秦表哥
(I promised)
我答应过你
(I wouldn't get in between you and Qiu Yan.)
不会妨碍你和姐姐
(Qiu Yan is still alive.)
如今姐姐还活着
(It is unsuitable for me to stay here any longer.)
我也不便再住在这别院里了
(I hope you will forget about me soon.)
期望表哥尽快忘掉珉儿
(At least, then,)
至少这样
(you wouldn't hate me and despise me anymore.)
表哥不会再恨我 厌我
She is weak and vulnerable.
她弱不禁风
Wherever could she go?
能到哪儿去呢
No. I have to find her.
不行 我得去找她
Wait!
不
Sir!
爷
We don't have a single clue right now.
我们没有任何线索
Searching for her right now
现在去
is as if looking for a needle in the sea.
无疑大海捞针
And she is avoiding you and hiding from you.
而且她有意躲着您
How are we going to find her?
我们该怎么去找她呀
I failed Qiu Yan,
我负了秋嫣
and now I have failed Qiu Min too.
如今又负了秋珉
Liang Yi was right.
梁翊说得对
I am not a man.
我真不是个男人
Mother.
妈妈
Qiu Min.
三妹妹
Where did you go?
你去哪儿了
You had us worried to death.
可让我们担心死了
Qiu Yan went looking for you as well.
二妹妹也去找你
But she never came back.
一去不回
Fortunately, Lord Liang sent us a letter
幸好梁大人带信回来
to let us know that she was all right.
说她一切安好
All that matters is that you're back.
回来就好 回来就好
You didn't get seen on your way back,
你这一路走回来
did you?
没有被人看见吧
I was wrong.
是珉儿不好
I made you guys worry about me.
让大妈和姐姐担心了
It's all right.
没事 没事
Third Young Lady.
三姑娘
Didn't you tell us not to look for you?
不是不让我们找你吗
What?
怎么
Back with your tail in between your legs?
夹着尾巴回来了
Madam.
姨娘
I'm sorry.
对不起
So you know you should be sorry, huh?
还知道对不起啊
How could you do what you did?
你之前那一出是人干的事吗
You had your sister take such a risk
你让你二姐姐冒这么大险
to go and look for you.
出去找你
Thankfully, my daughter is capable.
幸好我女儿有本事
She even managed to become Marquis Weiyuan's concubine.
还能留在侯府做夫人
Unlike someone else
不像某些人
who still had to come back in shame...
还得灰溜溜地回来
That's enough.
行了
No one will take you as a mute even if you don't speak.
你不说话没人把你当哑巴
Go inside and rest.
进屋歇着吧
First Sister-in-law.
大嫂
Was I wrong?
我说得有错吗
She caused us so much trouble.
你说她给我们惹了这么大麻烦
Why do you make it sound
怎么现在回来
as if she did a good deed by coming back?
倒像是有功似的
We still have so much work to do,
这么多活没干呢
and you're letting her rest?
还让她歇着
I'll go and do the chores right away.
我这就去干活
Qiu Min.
三妹妹
I'll help you.
那我帮你一起吧
First Sister-in-law, don't be silly.
大嫂 你别傻
If you're nice to Yan'er,
对嫣儿上心
she can at least look after us.
嫣儿在侯府还能关照咱
To her?
对她
What could we possibly get?
咱能捞着什么
Old Madam, help me!
夫人 快来帮帮我
The paper kite is going to fly away!
纸鸢要飞走了
Quick!
快 快 快
You need to control it.
得控制
Look.
你说说
Here.
来
If not, the string will break.
否则啊 线会断的
Like this.
是这样啊
What a nice wind. With force.
好风啊 凭借力
Look.
你看看
Look at how high it is flying.
飞得多高啊
It's beautiful.
好美呀
It is flying so high.
飞得好高啊
Look.
你看
This is my first time trying it, so I only made a soft-winged kite.
第一次只做了一个软翅
Please teach me how to make a hard-winged kite and a long-string kite next time.
以后还请夫人教我做硬翅跟长串
You went through a lot of effort.
真是为难你了
I had a lot of fun today.
今日啊 我特别畅快
Old Madam,
夫人
did you know
你可知
His lordship wrote a book about investigations?
大人曾写过公案话本
How did you know?
你怎么知道
Did he show you the manuscript?
他给你看了手稿
I stumbled across it when I was looking for materials
我昨日找做纸鸢工具的时候
to make the paper kite yesterday.
无意间发现的
I've read it before
这个话本
when I still lived with my family.
我从前在家的时候就看到过
I loved it.
很是喜欢
I was upset for quite a while
当初还因为作者没有写完结局
when the author never wrote an ending back then.
抓心挠肝了好一阵子
I never expected that it was His lordship who wrote it.
没想到就是大人写的
But why did he stop writing?
只是他后来为什么不写了呢
Yi'er
以前的翊儿
was completely different back then.
跟现在完全不一样
He was playful and boisterous.
爱闹爱笑
Music, chess, literature, art. He could do everything.
琴棋书画无一不通
Everything has changed
自从六年前
since his father passed away
他父亲去世以后
six years ago.
全变了
(Duke Lu was overbearing in his manners back then.)
当年卢国公行事霸道
(When the late marquis went hunting with His Majesty, he took advantage)
他趁着老侯爷随圣上去围猎之际
(of the situation and pretended to have shot his steed on accident.)
假装失手射了老侯爷的坐骑
(After he was injured, the late marquis lost a lot of blood)
老侯爷受伤之后失血过多
(and fell unconscious as he developed a high fever.)
继而昏迷高烧
(He passed away)
没过一日
(in less than a day.)
就撒手人寰
(Yi'er vowed he would avenge his father.)
翊儿发誓要为他父亲报仇
(So he put away all of the things he liked)
所以把之前所喜欢的物件
(in a chest)
全放在箱子里
(and never touched them again.)
再也不碰了
I've heard of this.
这事我听过
Four years ago, Duke Lu was exiled
四年前那位卢国公
because of a theft of a rice warehouse under his rule.
因治下的米仓失窃被贬去流放
He died of sudden illness during the journey.
流放途中 便暴病而亡
His lordship did that?
这是大人所为
Actually, before the late marquis passed away,
其实老侯爷临终前
he left Yi'er a letter.
给翊儿留了一封信
He repeatedly told him not to avenge him.
再三叮嘱不要报仇
Both of us wanted him to live a carefree life
我们都希望他无忧无虑
without worries or burdens.
逍遥自在地生活
But Yi'er was stubborn and persistent.
可是偏偏翊儿钻牛角尖
He kept everything to himself
什么事都放在肚子里
and wouldn't tell me anything.
不跟我说
In hindsight,
现在回想起来
I was a failure
我这个当娘的
as a mother.
真是失败
His lordship may not say it out loud,
大人他虽然嘴上不说
but in his heart,
但是心里
he respects you very much.
也是十分敬重您的
Who knows how he feels in his heart?
他心里想什么谁知道呢
Wan'er.
婉儿啊
Only when he took you as his concubine
唯独他纳你进府这件事啊
did I manage to see that he still had feelings and emotions.
我从他身上还看到了一点人情味
I'll be honest with you.
实话跟你说吧
At first, I liked you
起初我喜欢你
because I wanted to see Yi'er start a family
是希望看到翊儿成家
and carry on the family name.
延续香火
But now,
可现在
I've come to understand more and more
我越来越明白
why he thinks so highly of you.
他为何如此看重你
Wan'er,
婉儿
will you always stay with Yi'er?
你会一直陪着翊儿下去吗
(I recently captured bandits from Northern Liang.)
臣近日俘获北凉盗贼
(During the operation,)
抓捕途中
(Gao Yang and his clan had provided their full assistance.)
高阳一族全力协助
(They have made a great contribution.)
功不可没
(Back then, Duke Lu)
当年卢国公
(was corrupt and made little of the people's lives.)
贪赃枉法 草菅人命
(He endangered the people's lives.)
危害民生
(Memorial) (But his son, Gao Yang, served the nation.)
但其子高阳为国效力
(His loyalty is evident.)
忠心可鉴
(I implore Your Majesty to consider his loyalty)
臣恳请圣上
(and the fact)
念其忠孝
(that he is a descendant of the Grand Princess' clan,)
且是长公主族人
(to allow him to redeem himself with his merits,)
准其将功赎过
(restore his name and status)
恢复名誉优待
(to show Your Majesty's benevolence.)
以表圣上宽宏
Find a skilled craftsman
好生找个巧匠
and have them do as I say.
按我说的那般去做
Yes, sir.
是
I will be counting on you tomorrow.
明日拜托了
You have gone to painstaking lengths
梁大人为了秋家
for the Qiu Family indeed, Lord Liang.
不可不谓是苦心积虑啊
I was the one who sought out the Qiu Family back then.
当初是我自己寻上了秋家
Now, the Qiu Family is in trouble.
如今秋家落难
If I don't help them,
我若不顾
I would be too cold-blooded and lose the hearts of others.
岂不是寒了众人的心
Indeed.
是啊
Just like how you sought me out back then.
就如同梁大人当初寻上我一样
Anti-corruption efforts in the military were only carried out smoothly,
军中反贪顺利推行
all thanks to General He.
全依靠贺老将军
Now,
如今那些
those incapable sons of nobility and the influential have been removed
在其位不谋其职的世家子弟
from their positions.
被换下
The military is filled with capable talents.
军中皆是实干之人
A new culture has been implemented from top to bottom.
上行下效 风气一新
It is a major boost in morale.
士气大增
General He must be credited for this matter.
贺老将军居功至伟
Don't give me so much praise.
休要谬赞
I was merely forced to get on your boat.
我只不过是被梁大人绑上船的
Mother.
母亲
What did you need me for?
找我何事
Yi'er.
翊儿
I got a group of opera performers to come and perform today.
我叫了一班小戏
Watch the opera performance with me.
你啊 今天就陪我看戏
I still have work to do.
我还有公务呢
You have work every day,
公务天天有
but you don't get to enjoy the performances every day.
可是戏不是天天能看的
Besides, Yi'er,
再说了 翊儿
how long has it been since you watched a show with me?
你多久没陪我看戏了
You must watch it with me today.
今天啊 你非得陪我去
All right.
好吧
I am the newly appointed prefect
我是新上任的
(Autumn River) of Tianquan County, Murong Yuyan.
天泉县知府慕容玉言
If you have any grievances,
你们有何冤屈
please do tell me.
尽管向本官道明
I think the play Wan'er choreographed
我看 婉儿自己编排的戏
is much more interesting than the ones out there.
比外面的戏班有趣多了
As for you.
至于你
You impersonated a court official.
你假扮朝廷命官
You deceived His Majesty. You were disloyal.
欺君罔上 是为不忠
You oppressed the people.
你欺压百姓
You judged a murder case with bias. That is an injustice.
乱判命案 是为不义
(Autumn River)
像你此等不忠不义之人
and unrighteous people like you.
本官容你不得
This sword is meant
此把剑
to vanquish the demons in this world.
专治世间鬼魅
I will use your blood
我定要用你的血
to compensate all the wronged souls...
以嗟天下冤魂
and comfort all...
以慰嗟叹冤
the sorrowful souls.
魂
Come on. How was my performance?
怎么样 我演得怎么样嘛
It was all right, I guess.
中规中矩吧
Since you helped me
你既然帮我把
give the "Collection of Odd Occurrences" an ending,
大朔奇案录补完结局
when it is reprinted,
重新刊印之时
I will include your pen name
你的笔名啊
on it too.
也应续上
Really?
真的吗
I'll have to think it over properly then.
那我可得好好想想
I must think
我得想一个
of an astounding and unforgettable name!
一鸣惊人 过目难忘的好名字
Speaking of which,
话说回来啊
you've read a lot of books about investigations.
你看过这么多公案话本
Be completely honest.
凭心而论
What do you think of the "Collection of Odd Occurrences"?
奇案录到底怎么样
There are a lot of stories about investigations out there,
这世面上的公案话本虽多
but the "Collection of Odd Occurrences" is unlike any of them.
但奇案录跟它们都不一样
It may appear to be a story of solving cases,
奇案录看似写的是破案
but it is actually a story
但它其实讲的是
about a law enforcer, Murong Yuyan, and his ambitions and ideals.
刑名慕容玉言的抱负和理想
When I read this book,
我当时看此书时便想
I thought the author
写此话本之人
must have had a burning fire in his heart
心中定有熊熊烈火
that he wanted to use to shine and light up the world.
欲照天地清明
I'm not as good as you think I am,
我并没有你想得那么好
let alone half as good as the characters I wrote.
更不及笔下人物半分
I approached the He Family
我拉拢贺家
because I wanted to introduce political and military changes.
是为了推行军政变革
I wanted to marry Qiu Min
我求娶秋珉
because I wanted your father's support.
是想获得你父亲臂助
But my ambitions
可是因为我的野心
dragged your father
连累了你父亲
and all of the Qiu Family down.
和秋家这么多人
It is as you said.
就像你说的
I caused the suffering of so many.
是我害了那么多人
I'm sorry.
对不起
I only said that in a momentary lapse of anger.
一时气话
Why take it to heart?
你何必记在心上啊
Nobody is infallible.
智者千虑必有一疏
Much less you.
何况是你呢
I only said those words
我当时说那些话
because I had nowhere else to vent the anger in my heart.
是我这心中的怒火实在无处发泄
If you're still taking the blame
若此时你还把过错
for everything upon yourself,
大包大揽于自己身上
then you must be too opinionated.
那未免也太自以为是了吧
I've never had a peaceful night of sleep
我在劈柴处六年间
in the six years I've been at the Firewood Office.
没有一个晚上是睡得好的
Every night when it's quiet out there,
每到夜深人静的时候
there is always a voice questioning me
总有一个声音在质问我
if what I'm doing is right...
我做的这一切到底是对
or wrong.
还是错
I don't know about the other things,
别的事情我不清楚
but as far as the Qiu Family is concerned,
反正就秋家的事情而言
you never coerced my father.
我父亲没有受你胁迫
So you don't have to feel guilty or blame yourself.
所以你不用感到愧疚跟自责
Do you really think so?
你真的是这么想的吗
What do the sun and moon care
昭昭日月
about a few floating clouds?
何在乎些许浮云
What are a few setbacks and hardships
成大事者
when you achieve great things?
何在乎些许挫折坎坷
You wrote those lines yourself!
这都是你自己写的
How could you forget about them?
你怎么反倒忘了
Liang Yi. We're all ordinary people.
梁翊 我们都是普通人
Ordinary people
普通人做事情
are not perfect.
没有办法尽善尽美
But we can do our best
但我们可以做到尽力而为
and leave no regrets.
无愧于心
And that's enough.
足矣
So...
所以
Was my performance good?
我刚才演得好不好
It was very good.
好看至极
I knew it.
我就说嘛
Greetings, Your Majesty.
臣 叩见圣上
General He.
贺老
Liu Quan said you had a treasure for me.
刘全说你有宝物献给朕
What is so precious
是什么好东西
that you had to make the trip yourself?
还值得你亲自跑一趟
It is indeed a divine item.
确是天物
I dare not be any less cautious.
臣不敢怠慢
Please take a look, Your Majesty.
请圣上过目
My son acquired this by chance when he was patrolling the frontier
此乃我家犬子驻守北境巡边之时
at the northern borders he was stationed at.
于边陲偶然所得
Such a large Night-luminescent Pearl is already a rare find,
如此硕大的夜明珠本已罕见
but what's even more peculiar
更奇的是
is the flying deity
中间
that can be faintly seen in the center
隐隐约约可见一衣带翻飞的仙人
and the natural formation around it
旁边浑然天成
that is shaped like clouds.
祥云的纹路
There are countless rare treasures in the palace.
宫里的奇珍异宝多的是
There is nothing His Majesty hasn't seen before.
皇上什么宝贝没见过
How did a Night-luminescent Pearl
一颗夜明珠
become a heavenly sign of auspiciousness?
怎么就成了天大的祥瑞
There is a precious pearl in the Hongzhen Sutra
弘真经中有一宝珠记载
named Dengxian Pearl.
名为登仙珠
It is said that when the immortal, Hongzhen,
说的是当年弘真仙人
was on a pilgrimage to the northern borders,
在北境苦旅时
he grasped the true meaning of the five realms of existence.
参透五道众生真谛
Finally, the Empyrean Fairy inducted him,
终得九天玄女感应
and he ascended to heaven as a deity.
而后羽化登仙
Before he did,
登仙之际
he used the spiritual energy of heaven and the earth
他用天地灵气
to concentrate his years of cultivation into a pearl of immortality
将多年修为凝成一颗仙珠
and left it in the mortal realm.
遗留于俗世之中
But there were no records
可登仙珠具体是何模样
of what the pearl looked like.
并无记载
I had Song Jin find a skilled craftsman
我让宋锦找高人
and had him refine the Night-luminescent Pearl.
帮忙打制夜明珠
To make it appear like
让珠子内啊
there was a natural formation
隐隐似有一仙人
of a deity ascending to heaven
飘飘然登仙之景
that could be faintly seen within it.
看上去浑然天成
General He's eldest son
贺老将军的长子
is stationed at the northern border.
常年驻扎于北境边界
It makes sense for him to acquire the pearl.
由他带过来 合乎常理
His Majesty reads the Hongzhen Sutra religiously every day.
圣上日日熟读弘真经
Naturally, he would make the connection.
定能将此物与登仙珠联系起来
It is written in the Hongzhen Sutra
弘真经中记载
that the fated person who obtains this item
若有缘之人拿到此物
will be graced by the Empyrean Fairy's presence.
九天玄女将受到感应
She will find a virgin
在俗世中
to use as her vessel of reincarnation in the mortal realm
找一处子作为自己的转世
to cleanse the pearl of all mundane.
为宝物洗脱尘俗之气
When the Empyrean Fairy has consecrated the pearl,
待九天玄女开光之后
praying and offering to the pearl every day and night
日夜供奉此珠
will prolong one's life.
便能延年益寿
As such,
因此
as long as we present His Majesty with the Dengxian Pearl,
只要献上登仙珠
His Majesty will want to search
圣上就会想寻找
for the reincarnation of the Empyrean Fairy.
转世玄女的下落
I thought the matter of auspiciousness was merely myth and imagination.
本以为祥瑞一事天马行空
But it turns out the Hongzhen Sect itself is a mystery.
原是这弘真门本就玄乎其玄
Since ancient times,
自古啊
those who hold the highest power
身处权力之巅的人啊
have yearned for longevity
都渴望长生不老
and to rule forever.
大权永握
His Majesty is no exception.
圣上也不例外
The Grand Preceptor and the Hongzhen Sect are well-favored
国师和弘真门深得宫里的信任
because they appealed to His Majesty's desires.
原来是迎合了圣上的这层心思
But the Grand Preceptor might not be as devout as he seems.
只是我看这国师未必有多虔诚
Would he really buy the idea
他真的会相信
of the Dengxian Pearl descending into the mortal realm?
登仙珠降世这样的说辞吗
He has no reason not to.
他没有理由不信
His Majesty is up in years
如今圣上年事已高
and plagued by illnesses.
疾病缠身
It is inevitable that His Majesty would doubt the effectiveness of cultivation and alchemy.
难免不会对炼丹修行产生疑虑
With such an auspicious sign delivered right to his door,
有这送上门的祥瑞
the Grand Preceptor will definitely make a huge deal out of it
国师定会为弘真门
for the Hongzhen Sect's sake.
大大吹嘘一番
What joyous news, Your Majesty!
圣上 大喜啊
Years of sincerity have finally moved the immortal, Hongzhen,
多年诚心终于打动弘真仙人
and you've been rewarded with auspiciousness.
得祥瑞降世嘉奖
According to the Hongzhen Sutra,
若按经书所言
the Dengxian Pearl should appear together
登仙珠应该与转世玄女
with the Empyrean Fairy.
一同出现
Precisely.
正是
With the Dengxian Pearl consecrated by the Empyrean Fairy,
这登仙珠有玄女开光
Your Majesty will surely be in good health
圣上必能龙体康健
and live a long life.
万寿无疆
But where is the Empyrean Fairy?
可是玄女呢
According to the Hongzhen Sutra,
据经书上记载
the Empyrean Fairy
玄女会找世上
will reincarnate into the body of the purest woman.
最纯净的女子下凡转世
This woman must be a virgin,
此女子必是处子之身
and she must be untainted by all impurities.
不沾任何的污秽血腥
The Empyrean Fairy has a water alignment.
这玄女在仙道中属水
So she will appear by the water
所以将衣着白色
dressed in white.
出现在水的旁边
As for the exact location...
具体在什么地方呢
Your Majesty.
圣上
I have read a fortune.
臣已算了一卦
Please take a look, Your Majesty.
圣上 请过目
The place mentioned in the note
这纸中所指
will be where the Empyrean Fairy will appear.
就是玄女将出现之处
Good.
好
Greetings, Your Majesty.
参见圣上
Yan.
闫卿
I have summoned you here
朕让你来
to have you find someone for me.
是让你替我找个人
Imperial Commander Yan.
闫殿帅
The matter of the Empyrean Fairy is a matter of auspiciousness.
玄女之事 事关祥瑞
It is a matter of great importance.
兹事体大
You may only bring your most trusted subordinates with you.
你只可带着最心腹的人去
You must not reveal any of this to another.
绝不可吐露半点与他人
I will accomplish this task dutifully, Your Majesty.
臣 定当尽心
Go on.
去吧去吧
When will I be able to find the Empyrean Fairy?
何时才能寻到玄女呢
Your Majesty.
圣上
You need only concentrate on your cultivation.
您只管潜心修炼
The Empyrean Fairy will surely
只要心诚
sense your sincerity as long as you are sincere.
玄女自有感知
Truly?
是的
Rest assured.
您放心
All right.
好 好
Well then, Your Majesty,
那圣上
I must return to continue my concoction now.
臣也回仙观继续炼丹了
All right.
好
Go on.
去吧 去吧
I shall take my leave now.
微臣告退
Grand Preceptor.
国师
The pearl appeared out of the blue.
这珠子平白无故地出现
There is no Empyrean Fairy whatsoever.
哪来的什么转世玄女啊
What if His Majesty fails
圣上若是找不到
to find it?
该怎么办啊
In that case, we'll just tell His Majesty he was not sincere enough
到时候就说他心不诚
and comfort him.
再随便安慰几句
What could possibly happen?
能有什么事啊
So,
所以
we only have to arrange for the "Empyrean Fairy"
我们只要将玄女
to appear at the location the Grand Preceptor mentioned,
安排在国师预言会出现的位置
and our plan will be a success.
此事可成
But
只是
based on what you said...
按你说的
The Grand Preceptor will perform divination to determine the direction.
国师会打卦寻找玄女的方位
How will we find out then?
这我们如何得知
I have my ways.
我自有主意
The day after tomorrow, you will go to the Imperial Guards Camp as usual.
后日你按惯例去到禁军大营
Make sure you find out
务必要在闫大人身上
where Imperial Commander Yan will be headed.
套出他后日行动所去方位
Understood.
明白
After you complete this task,
做完这件事
I will redeem you.
我打算将你赎出教坊司
Go and find someone suitable,
出去找个可意的人
and settle down.
好好过日子
My lord.
大人
Do you no longer require my services?
您是不再需要小小了吗
The Firewood Office has been faring well over the past few years.
劈柴处这几年风头正盛
His Majesty favors me as well.
圣上也很信任我
You've worked hard for the past few years.
这几年啊 你也受累了
It's time for you to live peaceful days
也该过些舒心的日子
in comfort and bliss.
享享福
You are lying, my lord.
大人撒谎
Under the current rule of Yuan Lang, the Main Administrative Office
如今元阆治下的总章衙门
is eying you like a tiger watching its prey.
正对您虎视眈眈
But you want me to leave the Royal Academy at a time like this?
您却这个时候要小小出教坊司
You are the Firewood Office's best informant.
你是劈柴处最好的眼
If you get any other ideas,
如果你有了别的心思
it would be dangerous for you.
这对你很危险
So you still found out.
大人还是知道了
So...
所以
I can no longer even be Your lordship's informant.
我连大人的眼都做不得了
You and I met when we were less eminent.
看来我与大人识于微时
We have known each other for three years.
三年相处
But that cannot be compared to the three months you've known her.
却抵不过她三个月
What do you mean?
这话从何说起啊
You like Qiu Yan,
大人喜欢秋嫣
don't you?
不是吗
If you don't want to take this job,
如果这案子你不愿意做的话
it's all right.
没有关系
I'll think of something else.
我会另想办法
But no matter what,
但是赎身的事情
I will help
无论如何
to redeem you.
我都会替你办好
No.
不
I will accomplish every task
大人交给小小的事
you ask of me.
小小怎么都会去做的
Please do not
也请大人
help to redeem me as well.
不要替小小赎身
I have been here for three years.
教坊司三年
The Royal Academy is my home now.
这里已经是我的家了
I will bring some refreshments for you.
我去给大人拿些茶点过来
Men.
兄弟们
I am in a good mood today.
今本殿帅高兴
Drink to your heart's content!
尽管喝 酒管够
Drink!
喝
Congratulations, Imperial Commander.
恭喜殿帅
It's a joyous occasion for all!
同喜同喜
Drink!
喝 喝 喝
Raise your cups!
端起酒杯来
Drink as much as you like.
随便喝啊
Good wine.
好酒
Drink more then.
好酒就多喝
Give me another.
再来一杯
Fill it up.
满上 满上
Here.
来来来
You drink some too.
你也喝点
Come! Drink!
来来来 喝喝喝
Miss Xiaoxiao.
小小姑娘
I just love your cold as ice demeanor.
我就喜欢你这冷若冰霜的派头
Before you,
在你面前
even a shiver would numb my entire body.
打个寒颤那都浑身麻酥得很哪
I wonder, what has you
不知因为何事
in such a good mood today, Imperial Commander Yan?
今日闫殿帅如此开心
Me?
我呀
I'll be honest with you.
与你说认真的话
I got an important mission today.
今天我接了个大任务
One like never before.
这个任务不比以往
If I complete it,
要是完成了
a great reward
那可是天大的恩赐啊
will await me!
等着呢
What mission would merit such a great reward?
什么任务 这么大的恩赐
Finding someone.
找人
Who?
何人
I must abide by military discipline.
军纪如山哪
I can't tell anyone that.
这个 我可不能说呀
Not even me,
连我也不能说吗
Imperial Commander Yan?
闫殿帅
Well, if Miss Xiaoxiao wants to know,
要是小小姑娘想知道的话
I could perhaps make an exception.
那倒未必
All right.
好 好 好
Sir!
爷
This is the information we received from our...
这是我们的人从闫
Information we got from Imperial Commander Yan.
闫殿帅那儿传来的消息
Didn't you say your informant
你不是说你的人
would be able to get us information about the direction to go?
可以打听出寻人的方向
This is just a list of items.
这只是一个物品单子
Imperial Commander Yan has held His Majesty's trust for many years.
闫殿帅受圣上信赖多年
I guess we won't be able to get it out from him.
看来是套不出话了
She could only write us
她只能把看到的
about what she saw.
都写在上面
I understand now.
我懂了
Based on the items prepared for tomorrow's departure,
从明日出行的物件入手
we might be able to tell which direction they will go.
兴许可以判断出所去的方向
The Hongzhen Sutra says
经书上说
that the Empyrean Fairy will appear at places with water.
玄女会出现在水边
There are not many water sources in the capital.
京城水源地并不多
We only need to figure out the general direction,
只需要锁定大体的方向
and we'll be able to identify where the Empyrean Fairy will show up.
就能定位玄女出现处
One would bring a raincoat to avoid getting wet.
带着蓑衣自然是为了避雨
But it's the middle of summer right now.
可现在正值夏日
There hasn't been a drop of rain in days.
连日干旱
Where would there be rain?
哪里会下雨呢
The Huilong Mountain in the west has a unique topography.
西边的回龙山山势奇特
There are often rain showers in that area.
就常有阵雨
Is there a water source around that area?
那处可有水源
Yes.
有
The Jinxian Spring.
叫金线泉
But this Jinxian Spring extends for tens of lis.
但是这个金线泉漫延数十里
The range is far too wide.
范围太广
They will need wooden clogs.
要用到木屐
That means they must need to pass through shallow waters.
必然是要经过浅水处
It's a place where you would need to wade.
需要淌水的地方
That must be upstream, then. Around the spring cave.
那便是溪水上游泉洞处
The water is shallow, and you will need to wade through it.
水流浅 需涉水前行
Song Jin.
宋锦
This place.
这个位置
Have you memorized it?
记住了吗
Tomorrow, follow the marked location
明日你按照标记处
and bring our "Empyrean Fairy" to wait for them there.
带着我们的玄女去等他们
Understood.
是
Let's go and see them.
去看看她们
Let's go.
走
Qiu... Qiu Mei...
秋 秋玫
I... Qiu Mei...
民 民女秋玫
I, Qiu Mei, greet His Majesty.
民女秋玫拜见圣上
Are you the daughter of the criminal, Qiu Yi?
你可是罪臣秋家之女
Aren't all of you supposed to be dead?
你们不是已经都死了吗
Yes.
是 是
No! That's not it.
不是 不是的
Yes. We... The Qiu Family...
是 我 我们秋家
The Qiu Family encountered an accident while we were on Bian River.
在汴河遭遇船难
Then...
后来
After that...
然后
Qiu Mei.
大姑娘啊
We are all
我们这一家子人
counting on you.
可都指望着你呢
But you're a nervous mess!
你这是要急死谁呀
My daughter
我们家姑娘
has never told a single lie her entire life.
从小半句谎话没有说过
Asking her to lie before His Majesty
眼下在金銮殿上
at the Hall of Supreme Harmony
万岁爷面前扯谎
is an impossible task for her.
这本来就是难为她嘛
Mother.
母亲
I had it all memorized.
我刚才真的背得好好的
But
可是
when she yelled at me just now,
刚才她猛地一喊我
I...
我
I forgot everything. I couldn't recall anything!
我就什么都想不起来了
Qiu Ying.
四姑娘
You're a brave one.
你胆子大的
Why don't you take her place instead tomorrow?
要不明日你去
I'm scared.
我怕
I can't do it.
我不行
Qiu Mei had been memorizing those lines for so long,
那段话大姐姐背了那么久
yet she still couldn't memorize them.
都没背下来
How could I memorize them in just one night?
我一个晚上如何背得下来
I'll go.
我去吧
I've been listening when Qiu Mei was memorizing her lines.
这两日我听玫姐姐练习
I've already memorized the lines.
词我早就记住了
Qiu Mei is doing this to save Father.
玫姐姐是为了救父亲
This is a crucial matter for the Qiu Family.
这是秋家的大事
As Father's legitimate daughter,
我作为父亲的嫡女
I have a duty to serve my family as well.
理应也该出份力
You can't.
不行
Why?
为什么
You've always been timid and weak-willed.
你一向胆小性子软
You are not fit for the task.
不适合面圣
Min'er.
珉姑娘
You've always been sheltered,
你小家碧玉的
and you have frail health.
身子又不好
You shouldn't involve yourself in this matter.
这事呢 你就别掺和了
Qiu Yan.
二姑娘啊
Look.
你看
If this plan succeeds,
这事如果办成了呢
then it would be a joyous occasion for all.
就皆大欢喜
But if it doesn't,
如果办不成
then we would have committed the crime of deceiving His Majesty.
那我们岂不是犯了欺君之罪
That's right.
是啊
Our men have only been exiled.
眼下爷们儿只是流放
Life may be hard for us at the Guangji Hall,
我们在广济院虽然日子苦了点
but it's better than having the entire family sentenced to death.
但是总比诛九族强吧
That's right.
就是
If we fail, we might lose our heads.
弄不成是要杀头的
Qiu Yan, you are not afraid of death,
二姑娘 你不怕死
but I am.
我怕
We are all women.
我们都是女人家
Even the men in our family are of no use now.
家里多少爷们都不中用了
Will we women
靠我们
be able to do it?
能成吗
If you ask me,
要我看呀
I think we shouldn't take the risk.
咱别冒这个险了
Yan'er.
嫣儿
Just be good and stay at the Marquis's residence as Madam Su.
你就好好在侯府当你的小夫人
Just send us some money now and then.
平日多送点银子回来
That'll be enough to take care of us.
也算是挂念大家了